In the last video, we created a tetrahedral mesh for the mussels.
지난 영상에서는 근육용 테트라헤드럴(사면체) 메쉬를 만들었습니다.
Let's go ahead and save this and create a new flesh asset.
이걸 저장하고 새 Flesh 에셋을 만들죠.
Here, I'm going to call this Mussel Setup Flesh Acid.
여기서는 이름을 'Muscle Setup Flesh Asset'으로 하겠습니다.
And same thing, create a new data flow graph.
같은 방식으로 새로운 Dataflow 그래프를 생성합니다.
So in here, this is a brand new data flow graph.
이 화면은 완전히 새 Dataflow 그래프입니다.
The first thing we're going to do is make sure that we can import
먼저 우리가 할 일은,
the tetrahedral mesh we just created.
방금 만든 테트라헤드럴 메쉬를 가져올 수 있는지 확인하는 것입니다.
So let's go ahead and create a Get Flesh Asset node.
그래서 Get Flesh Asset 노드를 하나 만듭니다.
And over here, let's find our tetrahedral mesh.
그리고 여기서 우리 테트라헤드럴 메쉬를 찾죠.
There we go. That's our tetrahedral mesh for the mussels.
좋아요. 이게 근육용 테트라헤드럴 메쉬입니다.
After that, let's first assign mass and stiffness properties.
그다음으로 질량과 강성 속성을 먼저 지정하겠습니다.
The node we're calling is Set Flesh Default Properties.
사용할 노드는 ‘Set Flesh Default Properties’입니다.
And let's use the default one for now.
일단은 기본값을 그대로 쓰겠습니다.
Once we do that, you should see, if you go to Vertices,
그 다음, Vertices 탭으로 가보면
over here in the collection spreadsheet,
오른쪽의 컬렉션 스프레드시트에서
we should be able to see mass,
질량 값을 볼 수 있고,
and also stiffness properties and so on.
강성 등의 속성도 확인할 수 있습니다.
And for this one, let's go ahead and save this into a Flesh Asset terminal.
그리고 이 결과를 Flesh Asset 터미널에 저장하죠.
Make sure we save the Flesh Asset.
Flesh 에셋이 저장됐는지 확인하세요.
Now, if we press F, we should be able to see the mussel tetrahedral mesh here.
이제 F 키를 누르면 여기 근육 테트라 메쉬가 보일 겁니다.
Then click Start.
그 다음 Start(시작)를 누르세요.
This is a quick way to simulate things.
빠르게 시뮬레이션하는 방법입니다.
You can see it just drops to the ground.
바닥으로 그냥 떨어지는 걸 볼 수 있죠.
All right.
좋습니다.
Next, let's go ahead and set some constraints on the mussels,
다음으로 근육에 제약을 몇 개 걸어 보겠습니다,
so that we can drive muscle geometry with bones.
그래서 본으로 근육 지오메트리를 구동할 수 있게요.
Now, to do that, let's go ahead and start setting up a kinematic constraint.
이를 위해 먼저 키네마틱 제약을 설정하겠습니다.
The node we'll be calling is Set Flesh Bone Position Target Binding.
사용할 노드는 ‘Set Flesh Bone Position Target Binding’입니다.
And then over here for the mode, let's go ahead and use kinematic mode,
여기 모드는 키네마틱 모드로 두고,
because we're going to create some kinematic constraints between mussels and bones.
근육과 본 사이에 키네마틱 제약을 만들 겁니다.
And over here, the skeletal mesh, make sure we assign the skeleton,
그리고 스켈레탈 메쉬에서는 스켈레톤을 지정해야 합니다,
because we're binding the mussels to the animated skeleton.
애니메이션된 스켈레톤에 근육을 바인딩할 것이니까요.
And Search Radius, this is the radius threshold that we'll be using
Search Radius는 키네마틱 제약을 찾을 때 쓸
to find kinematic constraints.
반경 임계값입니다.
Basically, all the vertices of the mussels within this radius to the bones
본에서 이 반경 안에 있는 근육의 모든 정점이
will be bound kinematically.
키네마틱으로 바인딩됩니다.
Let's go ahead and give 1 as an initial radius.
초기 반경은 1로 주겠습니다.
And once we do that, we can visualize the kinematic constraints
이제 생성된 키네마틱 제약을 시각화하려면
we just created by calling Visualize Kinematic Faces.
‘Visualize Kinematic Faces’를 호출하면 됩니다.
So here you can see, this is all the kinematic constraints on the mussels.
보시다시피 이게 근육에 걸린 모든 키네마틱 제약입니다.
We can go ahead and start tweaking the radius if you think that's too much constraint.
제약이 너무 많아 보이면 반경을 조정해도 됩니다.
Yeah, this looks like a good amount to me.
네, 이 정도면 적당해 보이네요.
And that's our kinematic constraints.
이게 우리의 키네마틱 제약입니다.
We're also going to need some sprain constraints between the mussels
또 근육들 사이를 묶어 줄 스프링 제약도 필요합니다,
to hold the mussels together like a fascia does.
근막처럼 서로를 붙잡아 주도록요.
So, let's go ahead and call another node,
그래서 다른 노드 하나를 더 호출하겠습니다,
Set Protects Triangle Position Target Binding.
‘Set Protects Triangle Position Target Binding’.
And over here, you can see there's the position target stiffness,
여기에는 position target stiffness와
also the search radius.
search radius가 있습니다.
And let's check, allow sliding to allow the sprain to slide between muscles.
그리고 allow sliding을 체크해 근육 사이에서
And for the stiffness, let's set it up to 10.
스프링이 미끄러질 수 있도록 하겠습니다.
Search radius of 0.5.
stiffness는 10으로,
And before we do anything,
search radius는 0.5로 설정하죠.
let's slightly tweak the density here.
그 전에 밀도 값을 약간 조정하겠습니다.
The parameter I found to be optimal is
제가 써 보니 최적값은
1000 for density and 100,000 for stiffness.
밀도 1000, 강성 100,000 입니다.
And density actually matters when you set spring stiffness,
스프링 강성은 밀도, 즉 질량에 따라 스케일되기 때문에
because the spring stiffness is scaled with density or with mass.
밀도는 스프링 강성을 설정할 때 꽤 중요합니다.
Once we do that, let's go ahead and connect back to the terminal.
이제 다시 터미널에 연결하고,
And also visualize the spring constraints we just created
방금 만든 스프링 제약도
by calling visualize position targets.
‘Visualize Position Targets’로 시각화하겠습니다.
If you click this top right corner,
오른쪽 위를 클릭하면,
you can see these are the springs are visualized in red.
빨간색으로 표시된 스프링들이 보일 겁니다.
So it looks like a good amount to me again.
이 정도 양도 괜찮아 보이네요.
Let's start simulating things.
그럼 시뮬레이션을 시작해 봅시다.
So now we have kinematic constraints between muscles bones
이제 본과 근육 사이의 키네마틱 제약과
and also with spring constraints between muscles.
근육들 사이의 스프링 제약이 준비됐습니다.
So let's go ahead and bring the skeleton in.
다음으로 스켈레톤을 가져오죠.
Set the skeleton here.
여기서 스켈레톤을 설정하고,
You can see that.
보시는 것처럼 연결되었습니다.
Also going to need some animation.
애니메이션도 필요하니,
So let's go ahead and use the bicep curl.
bicep curl(이두컬) 애니메이션을 사용하겠습니다.
It's our animation.
이걸 애니메이션으로 쓰죠.
Now let's tweak the solver setting a little bit.
이제 솔버 설정을 조금 조정하겠습니다.
For the purpose of the tutorial,
이 튜토리얼에서는
we'll be running a quadistatic simulation,
준정적(Quasi‑static) 시뮬레이션을 실행할 겁니다,
meaning that there will be no inertia.
즉 관성이 없다는 뜻입니다.
So no dynamics in the simulation.
시뮬레이션에 동역학(다이나믹스)이 없다는 말이죠.
The reason we're doing that is that
그 이유는,
MO deformer is deterministic.
ML Deformer가 결정론적이기 때문입니다.
So for each pose, we want a deterministic result.
즉 각 포즈마다 결과가 항상 같아야 합니다.
We don't want any inertia or dynamics.
관성이나 동역학의 영향을 원하지 않죠.
So let's make sure we turn on this do quadistatics.
그래서 ‘Do Quasi‑statics’를 켜 두세요.
And also make sure we have the Gauss-Sadel solver enabled.
그리고 Gauss‑Seidel 솔버도 활성화합니다.
We have to design the Gauss-Sadel solver
이 Gauss‑Seidel 솔버는
specifically for quadistatic simulation.
준정적 시뮬레이션을 위해 특별히 설계되었습니다.
So make sure that's checked.
그러니 반드시 체크되어 있어야 합니다.
And that looks good to me.
지금 설정은 괜찮아 보이네요.
Remember, we can always tweak the solver settings,
솔버 설정은 언제든 조정할 수 있습니다,
such as number of steps,
예를 들어 스텝 수라든지,
and also a number of iterations
반복 횟수 같은 것들을요,
to reduce the numerical inertia.
수치적 관성을 줄이기 위해서입니다.
But for now, let's see what this looks.
일단은 이 상태로 어떻게 보이는지 보죠.
Right?
자,
You can see it's very unstable right now.
지금은 꽤 불안정해 보입니다.
That's because we have gravity turned on.
중력이 켜져 있기 때문이죠.
Remember, we need to run a quadistatic simulation.
우리는 준정적 시뮬레이션을 실행해야 하므로
So let's make sure we have gravity off.
중력은 꺼 두세요.
You can see there's a lot of inertia.
보시다시피 관성이 많이 보입니다.
And in this case, what you want to do is
이럴 때는 보통,
tweak number of sub-steps and number of iterations.
서브스텝 수와 반복 횟수를 조정합니다.
So let's go ahead and use 5 sub-steps and 20 iterations.
서브스텝 5, 반복 20으로 가 보죠.
And in this case, now the simulation is very likely to be offline.
이제 시뮬은 실시간보다는 오프라인에 가깝습니다.
So what we want to do is make sure we cache the simulation.
그래서 시뮬레이션을 캐시해 두는 게 좋습니다.
Let's go ahead and over here create a cache collection.
여기에서 캐시 컬렉션을 하나 만들고,
Let's create a new folder called cache.
cache라는 새 폴더를 만듭니다.
And let's call this Muscle Chaos Cache Collection.
이름은 ‘Muscle Chaos Cache Collection’으로 하죠.
Once you load the cache, you should be able to see the scroll bar here.
캐시를 로드하면 여기 스크롤 바가 보일 겁니다.
You can scroll this.
이걸로 스크롤할 수 있습니다.
It only shows the animation right now because we haven't simulated it yet.
아직 시뮬레이션을 돌리지 않았기 때문에
So let's go ahead and start simulating it.
지금은 애니메이션만 보이는 상태입니다.
Probably about 90 frames or so.
그럼 시뮬레이션을 시작하겠습니다.
And we can change the length of the simulation here.
대략 90프레임 정도면 될 겁니다.
Change the time range from 0 to 3.
여기서 시뮬 길이를 바꿀 수 있습니다.
So at 30 frames per second, 3 will give you 90 frames.
시간 범위를 0에서 3으로 바꾸면,
So let's go ahead and click this red record button.
초당 30프레임 기준으로 3초면 90프레임이 됩니다.
And you should see start to simulate.
자, 이제 빨간 녹화 버튼을 누르세요.
Now we just finished our simulation.
시뮬이 시작되는 걸 볼 수 있을 겁니다.
You can see we ran 90 frames.
방금 시뮬레이션이 끝났습니다.
If you scroll through the timeline here,
총 90프레임이 생성된 걸 볼 수 있죠.
you should see the muscles being simulated.
여기 타임라인을 스크롤해 보면,
So in the next video,
시뮬레이션된 근육이 보일 겁니다.
we'll start setting up some muscle properties
다음 영상에서는,
and start contracting muscles just to add on top of this.
근육 속성을 설정하고 수축을 추가해 보겠습니다.